Thanks to SquareSpace for making this
video possible and for helping launch my
new Mustard store. More on that after
this video. In the midst of the Cold War,
two Mig-25s race to intercept a threat
along the Soviet border. They're the
fastest interceptors ever built, and if
they really push their engines, they can
reach an incredible Mach 3.2. But it's
not enough. Because what they're chasing
can outrun and out-climb any threat. A
plane engineered to be invulnerable.
The Cold War locked the United States
and Soviet Union into a tense a struggle
for global influence and control. Both
sides poured enormous resources into
military technologies. But getting an
upper hand means knowing your opponent's
next move. And in the 1950s, little was
known about facilities deep within the
Soviet Union. An extensive network of
radar stations, surface-to-air missile
sites, and interceptor air bases kept the
Americans away. Until 1956, when U-2
spy planes began flying over the Soviet
Union. Neither fast nor stealthy, the U-2s had
one critical advantage. At 70,000 feet,
they could fly above Soviet air defenses.
U.S. President Eisenhower was even
assured, Soviet radars couldn't detect
the U-2 at such high altitudes. But it
turns out, the Americans were wrong. The
Soviets had tracked the U-2 since day one, and it was only a matter of time before
they'd be able to shoot one down. Simply
flying high wasn't enough. Even before
the U-2 began its surveillance missions,
there were already plans underway to
replace it. Because true impunity over
Soviet airspace would need a combination
of incredible speed, altitude, and stealth.
And this led the Americans to explore
some pretty radical spy plane concepts,
like a ramjet powered aircraft that
would be deployed from the bottom of a
supersonic B-58. But in 1959 the CIA
chose Lockheed to develop the next
generation of spy plane.
Meanwhile, the U-2 continued to fly over
the Soviet Union. But not for very long,
because in the spring of 1960, a Soviet
surface-to-air missile finally managed
to bring one down. The captured pilot and
wreckage were paraded around the Soviet
Union used as proof of Western
aggression. As tensions rose, now more
than ever the US needed a replacement
for the U-2.
And what Lockheed developed, would be
unlike any aircraft ever built. A plane
that nearly 60 years after its first
flight, remains the fastest air-breathing
jet to ever fly. Lockheed's
highly-classified spy plane would be
known as the A-12. Originally used by the
CIA for reconnaissance, the A-12 was also
developed into an interceptor prototype,
armed with air-to-air missiles, along
with a variant that could launch an
unmanned reconnaissance drone. But it was
the SR-71 Blackbird, a variant developed
for the Air Force that would go on to
serve for decades, while earlier versions
were quickly retired. The Blackbird could
cruise at Mach 3.2 right near the edge
of space, and do it for hours on end.
To achieve this, Lockheed's engineers had
to innovate pretty much everything from
scratch. To sustain such incredible
speeds the SR-71 and its predecessors
were powered by engines often described
as turboramjets. Below Mach 2 they
functioned like conventional
after-burning jet engines. But above that,
they behaved more like ramjets, as an
inlet cone adjusted to bypass air around
the engine and directly into the
afterburner. At mach 3.2 the SR-71's
exterior would heat up to beyond 500
degrees Fahrenheit, easily hot enough to
soften aircraft aluminum. Lockheed
engineers used titanium for 92 percent
of the aircraft, and in the 1960s this
required inventing entirely new
fabrication technologies. It's unusual
shape did more than just spook UFO
enthusiasts, it helped reduce its radar
signature as did its special black paint,
which earned the SR-71 its Blackbird
name.
The A-12 and SR-71 were first deployed
over North Korea and Vietnam, where they
were unsuccessfully targeted by over 800
surface-to-air missiles. But the spy
plane never flew into Soviet airspace. At
least not officially, because another
shoot-down over the Soviet Union would
be catastrophic.
So instead, the SR-71 flew along its
borders, using its powerful side-looking
radar and cameras to peer hundreds of
miles into Soviet territory. And that
frustrated the Soviets. In 1976, Viktor
Belenko defected to the west, by escaping
the Soviet Union in his Mig-25. He
described the frustration of trying to
intercept Blackbirds. The MiG's were
Mach 3 capable, but only for a few
minutes at a time. Not for hours like the
Blackbird. Nor could they climb to reach
the SR-71's incredible altitude. Even
their enormous R40 missiles lacked the
guidance needed to strike the SR-71
head-on. For years, the Blackbirds were
practically invulnerable. They could out
fly and out-climb any threat. But by the
1980s, Mig-31s were roaming the
skies, equipped with sophisticated radar
and long-range R33 missiles. They posed
a legitimate threat, as did a new
generation of Soviet surface-to-air
missiles. But the greatest threat to the
Blackbird wasn't an enemy missile or jet.
It was itself. No Blackbird was ever lost
on a mission, but more than a third of
the 50 built were destroyed in accidents.
One literally disintegrated around its
pilots. They were also enormously
expensive to operate. Each one siphoning
about 300 million dollars a year out of
America's defense budget. A fleet of
special aerial refuelers and a small army
of support and maintenance staff were
needed just to keep these planes mission
ready. And advances in spy satellites
aerial drones and the SR-71 s inability
to deliver surveillance data in real
time, diminished some of the plane's
utility. Add to that, politics and
infighting for defense budgets and by
the late 1980s, the SR-71's days were numbered.
They were officially retired in 1998,
with two sent to NASA for testing. The
technology behind the A-12 and SR-71 is
now well over fifty years old. Yet
somehow these incredible planes
still speak to us. Not about the past, but
the future. Leaving us with a sense of
wonder unlike any other in aviation
history. A few months ago, I launched my
Mustard site with SquareSpace. It was fun,
easy, and I did it literally in a few
hours. But now it's time to take it to
the next level. Using SquareSpace's
incredibly easy and intuitive e-commerce
features, I just launched the Mustard
online store. With SquareSpace's seamless
integration with Prtintiful, it took me
only a few hours to get up and running.
Be sure to check out the store, and let
me know if you have any requests for
Mustard swag. From start to finish, using
SquareSpace has been incredibly seamless,
intuitive, and fast. Whether you're a
photographer, blogger Youtuber, or run a
small business, make your next move with SquareSpace's all-in-one platform. Start
building your website for free at
squarespace.com/mustard, and when
you're ready to launch your website,
use the code Mustard for 10% off your
first purchase.